{
  "reference_number": "8265",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "Setting a firm target creates greater certainty and a more stable environment in which investment decisions can be made, early on.\n Doing so will ensure that the required investment into infrastructure is made early on and that 2050 targets have a higher chance of\n being met."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "Managing emissions reduction requires long-term behaviour change. Reducing methane from all sectors – including the agricultural\n\n sector - requires that technologies and new methodologies be introduced early on to combat the long-term effects of global warming\n resulting from greenhouse gas emissions. Clear policy signals and firm targets will stimulate investment into low emission agricultural\n\n techniques, ensuring that NZ is able to be more resilient in terms of managing its immediate natural environment, managing its\n emissions, and building long-term export market resilience by maintaining a competitive edge over international market competitors\n through related efficiency gains, and a strengthened brand and reputation for premium quality produce."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "By relying on domestic carbon sinks and abatement technologies, New Zealand will encourage local and foreign direct investment\n\n into solutions, and will avoid transferring emission abatement obligations overseas or buying in potentially sub-standard credits."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "The only scenario in which an adjustment might be considered necessary is one that demands an even more stringent target to be\n set (i.e. a target set against a baseline earlier than 1990)."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Five year cycles provide achievable short term goals that will enable New Zealand to stay on track for meeting its 2050 target."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "No - emissions budgets should not be able to be changed",
      "answer_index": 9,
      "notes": "Setting firm budgets signals stability and certainty to investors. The likely knock-on effect would be a stimulation of local investment in\n clean tech; and a stimulation of inflows of foreign direct investment into New Zealand as a hub for clean tech innovation. By contrast,\n on-going adjustments to any given carbon budget should only be done so in the context of where targets are being exceeded or\n\n outperformed i.e. if New Zealand’s emissions abatement trajectory is on a steeper downward curve than originally estimated, the\nbudgets may be adjusted to reflect that, and in doing so support sustained, strong performance."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "Unless New Zealand is outperforming its targets, in which case the budgets should be revised to sustain forward momentum."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Four key issues to consider are: 1. Decarbonising buildings: Adjusting current building standards and codes to support future carbon\ntargets. A focus on the following areas could deliver positive carbon reduction outcomes: a) All new building stock be mandated to\n\nadhere to green building codes and meet sustainability criteria. The minimum mandatory requirement be at least Home Star 6, in\nterms of energy efficiency. Future-proofing new builds should be a primary consideration in terms of capturing the potential for low\n\ncarbon emission energy generation and storage (i.e. solar conduit battery use and electric vehicle charging capacity in all new builds).\nb) The existing housing stock of 1.8 million homes - 800,000 of which are currently not adequately insulated - represents a significant\n\nopportunity and challenge in terms of reducing emissions, with particular regard to Government’s recent legislation relating to\nmandatory heating requirements. The lack of affordable insulation and energy efficient heating appliances, energy-related emissions\nmay be exacerbated by an initial supply shock (where demand outstrips supply). Government should therefore consider whether the\n\nexisting policy framework is fit-for-purpose in terms of transitioning to a low carbon economy and whether New Zealand be looking to\nother frameworks i.e. that of the UK where energy rating systems have been introduced, and where subsidies and tax reliefs are\n\nleveraged to stimulate investment into and market growth of insulation and energy efficiency products. c) In view of the forthcoming\nBuilding Code review, building standards such as H1 Energy Efficiency Standard (NZS 421:2009), should be reviewed with the\n\nobjective of mandating minimum standards that deliver carbon savings through energy efficient buildings. The current requirements\nare currently inadequate and should be tightened. 2. Renewables and clean tech: Leveraging appropriate policy tools to support\nGovernments long-term carbon reduction target through renewable energy generation and EV charging infrastructure. For example,\n\nmanage the anticipated largescale uptake of EVs and associated energy demand management, subsidies and taxes could be\nleveraged by: - creating an environment conducive to fast-tracking much needed investment in EV charging infrastructure -\n\nsupporting the build out of distributed energy with energy storage, and/or district heating and cooling (with storage) - sidestepping a\npotential demand crunch on existing energy sources, transmission and grid infrastructure. - increasing low carbon utility-scale\n\nrenewable energy generation (i.e. fast tracking consented utility-scale onshore and offshore wind and ground mounted solar arrays,\nhydro energy and more). Encourage investment into infrastructure that supports nascent technologies such as - hydrogen fuel cells\n\n2. Domestic food supply security: Transport emissions associated with increased food imports will negatively weight the carbon\nbudget. A recent report from HortNZ indicates that on the current population growth trajectory, demand will outstrip future supply of\ndomestic vegetables by 2020. Transport emissions associated with increased food imports will negatively weight the carbon budget.\n\nDomestic food supply is pivotal to carbon targets being met, given that food represents the greatest portion of consumption\nemissions (32% of Auckland’s household emissions according to the 2014 report by Motu Economic Research– Greenhouse Gas\n\nEmissions New Zealand: A preliminary Consumption-based analysis (Romanos, Kerr and Will); and food and restaurants accounting\nfor 30% of Auckland’s per capita consumption emissions according to C40 Cities consumption emissions data report 2018. Careful\n\nassessment of land allocation for housing development is urgently required (balancing housing vs food security - reference the\nHortNZ 2017 report); ensuring prime growing land is protected from housing development; and that domestic supply of vegetables\ncan meet demand; and that climate change and carbon reduction is embedded in land-use and planning policy. 4. Public transport\n\ninfrastructure: Citing the respective Motu Economic and Public Policy Research and C40 Cities findings for Auckland’s consumption\nemissions, transport accounts for the second-largest share of emissions from households (27% - Motu) and individuals (23% - C40\n\nCities). Ensuring that adequate investment is allocated to public transport infrastructure, particularly in new, high growth areas such\nas South and North Auckland, is key to reducing per capita carbon emissions. Plans tabled by Greater Auckland (congestion free\n\nnetwork and Regional Rapid Rail) merit consideration. In terms of who the government should be working with, strategic partners\nwould include: Communities – Behaviour change is pivotal to New Zealand meeting its carbon targets, in terms of reducing\n\nhousehold carbon emissions. Communities should be actively engaged, educated, encouraged and incentivised to prioritise energy\nefficiency, sustainable travel and low carbon consumption habits. Large and medium-sized businesses are also key partners with\nregard to their influence in shaping consumer behaviour and related environmental outcomes. Local Boards, councils and community\n\ngroups are also primary stakeholders, holding valuable knowledge in terms of material opportunities in any given area and holding\nvaluable insight into effective community engagement methods; and effective programme deployment."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Makes decisions itself in respect of the number of units available in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 10,
      "notes": "The Climate Change Commission will be comprised of New Zealand’s leading minds/sector/subject matter experts. It will be well-\ninformed to take such decisions, as an independent body."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "The balance may be further improved if business expertise was added to the mix, with the result being a Commission that is more\nrepresentative and informed - to the extent that it can set reliable targets independent of government. Private sector representation\n\ncould potentially be included on a rotational basis, to improve accountability and avoid the risk of perceived bias."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes, in terms of ensuring that risks are well understood and that the policy framework in place addresses these risks and enables\n\ndecisive action to be taken to diminish, mitigate or pre-empt risks."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Mandated reporting requirements will serve to improve transparency and will assist organisations and Government in more effective\n\nrisk management."
    }
  ]
}
